Guide to the Stanford University, Controller's Office, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Controller's Office, records
1900-1957
SC0048
Stanford University. Controller's Office.
23 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Access Terms
Stanford University. Controller's Office.
Collection Contents
- Records
  - University Record Books
    - Treasurer's Statements book, 1906-1910, Cash Receipts and Disbursements 1907-1911, Balance sheet 1907-1911
    - Journal #1 year 1891-1893 (Leland Stanford) – journal record of each deposit and disbursement
    - Journal 1893-1897 (Leland Stanford) – journal record of each deposit and disbursement
    - General Journal, June 1909
    - [THIS VOLUME REMOVED AND ADDED TO SC 387]
    - Journal Ledger, entries August 1909-April 1914
    - Journal Ledger, entries May 1914-July 1917
    - Journal Ledger, entries August 1917-Sept. 1919
    - Journal Ledger, plant entries August 1911-Sept. 1919
    - Ledger #3, Jane L. Stanford, Jan. 1902-May 1903
    - Day Book, Journal, Cash Book #4, April 1, 1898-April 19, 1901
    - Day Book, Journal, Cash Book #5, April 19, 1901-March 2, 1903
    - Day Book, Journal, Cash Book #6, March 7, 1903-May 29, 1903
    - Ledger #1, Manager's Ledger, Plant Assets, 1911-1919
    - Ledger #1, University Accounts, 1891-1893
    - Ledger #2, University Accounts, 1893-1899
    - Ledger #3, University Accounts, 1899-1902
    - Ledger #4, University Accounts, 1902-1903
    - Ledger #1, University Accounts, June-December 1903
    - Ledger #2, University Accounts, 1904-1906
    - Ledger #3, University Accounts, 1906-1908
    - Ledger #4, University Accounts, 1908-1911
    - Ledger #5, University Accounts, 1911-1912
    - Ledger #6, University Accounts, 1913-1915
    - Ledger #7, University Accounts, 1915-1917
    - Ledger #8, University Accounts, 1918-1919
    - Voucher Record #1, ledger, 1903-1906
    - Voucher Record #2, ledger, 1906-1908
    - Voucher Record #3, ledger, 1909-1913
    - Voucher Record #4, ledger, 1913-1914
    - Voucher Record #5, ledger, 1915-1916
    - Voucher Record #6, ledger, 1916-1917
    - Voucher Record #7, ledger, 1917-1918
    - Record of Departmental Requisitions and Expenditures #2, 1909-1910
    - Ledger, Tax Records on Bonded Warehouses, 1904-1913, and record of constructions contracts, 1912-1913 (Vina Ranch)
    - Cash Book #1, 1903-1905
    - Cash Book #2, 1905-1908
    - Cash Book #3, 1908-1910
    - Cash Book #4, 1911-1913
    - Cash Book #5, 1913-1915
    - Cash Book #6, 1915-1917
    - Cash Book #7, 1917-1919
    - Cash Book #8, 1919 through August
    - Journal #3 Lane Hospital, April 1900-May 1904
    - Ledger Hospital Accounts, 1908-1912
    - Journal Ledger Lane Hospital, 1908-1912
    - Journal Ledger Lane Hospital, 1912-1916
    - Loans Receivable, 1908-1919
    - Bond Ledger, interest accruals, 1912-1915
    - Bond Ledger, interest accruals, 1915-1919
    - Bond Ledger, interest accruals, 1919-1920
    - Bond Ledger, interest accruals, 1919-1922
    - Repairs on Campus Houses, 1911-1913
  - Vina and Durham Ranch Record Books
    - Voucher Register #1, Vina Ranch, May 1913-Arpl 1916
    - Voucher Register #2, Vina Ranch, May 1916-Nov. 1919
    - Ledger, dairy units, Stanford Vina Ranch, lease records
    - Ledger, Stanford Ranches, 1917-1919
    - General ledger, Vina Ranch, 1913-1917
    - Record Stallions and Mares, 1871-1902
    - Stock Book, New York Agency, Record of Shipments and Sales of Wine and Brandy, 1903-1908
    - Ledger, Vina Ranch, Customers ledger, 1916-1919
    - Ledger, Vina Ranch, Customers ledger, 1909-1915
    - Cash Book #3, Vina Ranch, 1913-1917
    - Cash Book #4, Vina Ranch, 1918-1919
    - Stock on Hand (horses) Palo Alto and Vina, January 1, 1901
    - Journal #2, Vina Ranch, May 1913-October 1919 (2 volumes)
    - Sanford Vina Ranch, Sales Journal, 1917-1919
    - Stock Record, Palo Alto Stock Farm, Record of Horses, 1891-1903 (2 volumes)
    - Stock Journal and Ledger, the Vina Agency
    - Book of Stock Certificates, Shares in Vina Agency
    - Herd Register, Cows and Bulls, 1904-1915
  - Additional University Books
    - Board Ledger 1892-93, 1896 (Encina and Roble Halls)
    - Ledger [board] 1902-03 (Encina and Roble Halls)
  - RECLASSED ITEMS
    - Encina Hall Register, October 1917-November 1919 REMOVED AND ADDED TO SC 387
- Records, Accession ARCH-2000-228
  - Statistical Analysis Income and Expense, 1922-1967 (handwritten ledger pages) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Enrollment Statistics and Tuition Rates by Academic Year, 1891/92-1952/53 (handwritten ledger pages) (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Records, Accession ARCH-2007-106
  - Book: SLAC Hearings before the Subcommittee on Research and Development and the Subcommittee on Legislation of the Joint Committee on Atomic Energy, Congress of the United States. 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Account book: Repairs to University-owned houses, 1916-1919, and pages giving appraised value, repairs, rent, and water; loan fund accounts 1916-1919 [seem to be mostly funds for students]; accounts of individual contractors/companies for work on University buildings, 1915-17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Binder on major construction projects; roads, streets and utilities; and Lane Hospital. Information dates from 1920-49 and primarily covers costs, with some architect and contract information. There is a list of the projects in the front of the binder. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alumni Jordan Medical Scholarship Fund, 1921-34 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Braly, Elizabeth Madison. List of furniture, pictures, etc. (for the Stanford Museum), 1936-41 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Busch, Niven. Gift document, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cubberley, Helen. Gift and assignment of royalties and other records, 1911-26 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Herzstein, Morris. Last will and testament, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miedel, Russell J. Gift of snuff bottles, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - PACE pledges 1963 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Petition of Board of Trustees regarding powers in respect to investment of trust funds, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Stanford, Jane Lathrop. Will and codicil, 1899-1900, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Stanford, Thomas W. Estate documents, 1911-1933 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Tuite, James Mitchell. Last will and testament, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - William Volker Fund. Original documents 1978 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Wilson, Amelia Evelyn Stevens, Trust of, 1931-48 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Wolters, Maria. Estate documents, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Stanford endowment, general maintenance, 1931-89 (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Stanford endowment, general maintenance, 1931-89 (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Cashbook for individual student residences 1945-46, with Board and Room recap for 1946/47; most entries without individual student names, except in the case of refunds (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Account book: R. H. Anderson Inc. (real estate and mineral rights) 1920s-1950s (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Account book: Bond acquisition and disposals, analysis, 1921-24 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Account book: Investment bonds, 1906-1998 (Box 4, Folder 3)